So I am going to define an operator a linear
operator called L pi, right so L pi is something
that is going to take a vector from the space
V where capital v is the space of all value
functions right so capital v is a complete
norm vector space of all value functions right
so I am going I am going to define an operator
L pi that takes an element in v to another
element in v right so how would define L pi?
L pi operating on V will give me back a function
that is right so v some element in capital
V which is some value function okay or some
element in capital v okay, so what is the
difference between saying there is some value
function and then saying some element in capital
v and wheni say a value function I am kind
of implicitly saying that there is a policy
for which that is the expected return right.
But when I say it is a point in the space
V that need not necessarily be true I mean
it is just some point in the s dimensional
space that need not necessarily exist a policy
corresponding to that function okay, so I
am just saying is some function V right the
dents in exists in that space capital V, between
what other space V to V does that make sense
means confusing to people less everybody's
on board right good right.
So what does my bellman equation tell me,
if you think about it the bellman equation
tells me right that is what my bellman equations
essentially is saying that I take this point
v pi in the space capital v I apply the operator
L pi on it whatever it gives me back will
be E pi right so likewise if I can define
an operator for the optimality equation it
will tell me that v star is a point in space
V such that if I apply the operator let us
call it l if I apply l on it will give me
back v star so this implies that E pi is what
is known as a fixed point of L pi right side
so if you think about it right so normally
I take some vector V I apply L pi on it okay.
It will go to some other point then I will
apply L pi on it will go to some other point
then I will apply L pi on it will keep moving
around right in space right if I apply L pi
on it and it stays there then I call it a
fixed point because I am using the defining
the operator through R pi and Lpi which themselves
are defined through pi right, I mean if you
looked at if you remember the definition no
it is not because the mapping is R pi I mean
mapping uses R pi and P pi is integral components
of it right.
It is not independent so the other one is
independent that there we will drop the dependence
the optimality equation has no dependence
on pi there will rock the dependence on fine
but the bellman equation has a as the pi in
it great so introduce you to something called
the Banarch fixed point theorem which is very
basic I mean believe it or not whatever we
are doing is very fundamental stuff right.
Very minimal math in terms of trying to prove
convergence and things like that because I
have restricted you to finite MDP's okay,
so the more heavy the more interesting math
comes when you start operating in the infinite
space state spaces right where I mean you
cannot write down simple results okay you
have to have lot of qualifications if your
MDP says that A satisfies this and that and
that and A satisfies this and that and that.
Then something will hold right but here you
can say some ways we can write very easy results
so I am going to use something called the
Banack fixed point theorem okay which will
which makes our life lot easy, right. I have
sounds like a very fancy term right Banach
space so what is a Banach space we already
know what a banach spaces complete norm vector
space is called a Banach space I just do not
get put off by terminology and we understand
this right.
So we know what a Banach space is a complete
norm vector space is a Banach space, so one
thing which I forgot I will introduce it let
this so some mapping t that map's points in
U to another point in U right we assume it
is a contraction mapping I will tell you what
is a contraction mapping in a minute okay
but you can think in kind of case water contraction
mapping is right it takes two points in space
then I take u and v I take T(u) and I take
T(V) right.
So T(u) and T(V) T will be closer to each
other than u and v were all right so that
is essentially contraction mapping so I will
write it down formally in a minute right,
then guess what we are.
Refer Slide Time: 08:38)
saying suppose use a Banach space and t is
a contraction mapping essentially things that
brings points together then that exists a
unique v star in U says that T of v starequal
to Vstar so that essentially means that T
has a fixed point.
T has a fixed point and it is a unique fixed
point okay and the second thing is for arbitrary
starting point V not if I keep repeatedly
applying T on V not right I will converge
to v star right.
So showing 1 does not imply to just because
a fixed point exists right repeatedly applying
it did not necessarily converge to the fixed
point in fact there are some results for certain
algorithms where we can show that that algorithm
itself has a fixed point then I mean or rather
v the system of equations you set up itself
as a fixed point but the iterative process
that you are using for solving it did not
necessarily converge to it okay.
There are cases that will happen but in this
case it says turns out that repeatedly applying
T that is essentially what the sequence is
at I start off with v not apply than it once
I get v one I apply T on it again I get v
two I apply ton I get v three and so on so
forth and I keep doing this then often enough
great I will end up in ?v star?^ is how many
times is often enough something we said even
we look at actual algorithms for solving these
problems.
But these are the things that exists a unique
?v star ?^ and this is a couple of things
that we need to show one is that the use of
Barnach space here again well it is a plan
it is a point in the V space is eigenvector
fine but I came as a point ,the point is that
is what we have been saying so what is V pi,
v pi is a vector that the first component
is v pi of 1 v pi of 2 v pi of 3 v pi of 4
This is a point I mean in S dimensional vector
space right cannot you see let us think of
a case where there are two states alone let
us state 1 state 2 right I define some policy
let us I am just going.
to look up something let us look at how it
works one I have too some arbitrary thing
have written and MDP for u right so I take
action one from state 1 I will go to state
2 and get a reward of 1 I will take action
one in state 2 I will get go to state 1 to
the robot of one I take action to in either
state 1 or state to I am going to stay there
with a robot of -1, okay.
Now let me define a policy so what is the
policy pi one is a oneand pi 2 is a 2 determine
am sorry pi 2 is a 1 . let us just define
a 1 a 1 for both right so what is the value
of state 1 and
you can do it easily enough but for some value
of gamma you can solve it or you can just
write the summation write it just 1 plus gamma
plus gamma square plus gamma cube I mean you
can solve the system of equation or you can
just tell me what is the limit of the summation.
Somebody tell me now if I think of this in
a two dimensional space yes I have a two dimensional
space this dimension is v pi of 1 this dimension
is v pi of 2 just a point, so
this point is whether we can think of defining
a pi dash of 1- of the
right so for any policy I choose like this
right pi of a 1 and pi of a 2 to whatever
things I choose I am going to end up with
some point in this space right.
So this is what I mean by the space capital
V so this is my space capital V and each value
function is a point in this space right I
mean I was hoping people have actually this
in their mind when they are nodding with whatever
saying earlier right so this is what I mean
by saying all of these things which we have
talked about right this being a complete norm
vector space everything we have talked about
is with this picture in mind so okay.
Does it make sense any questions about that
of course I just chose deterministic policies
to be easy right you could choose to Casting
policies you just have to write out this more
terms in this equation and this equation will
have the sum over pi of s comma a right and
then you solve it and then you get it right
so essentially the tricky part here turns
out showing that whatever mapping T you are
considering is a contraction mapping.
so if you can show whatever is the map that
you consider in this case we are going to
be considering L pi if you can show that L
pi is a contraction mapping right then you
get the rest of it for free yeah so that's
it essentially that i's what you have to do
to show us a convergence it is a contraction
mapping and just tell you in a minute I formally
write down what a contraction mapping is right.
So for sure okay it is it moves away so this
is what a contraction mapping is so u and
v where some distance apart after I applied
t on both of them they will be closer than
what they were earlier by a factor of at least
lambda where lambda lies between 0 and 1 a
1 excluded so the smaller the value of lambda
what does it mean the faster the points are
move together the more the contraction is
at the closer the value of lambda is 1.
The lesser the contractions obviously lambda
equal to one does not make sense right if
lambda is 1 then there is no contraction if
lambda 1 is T identity need not be and it
is, now just telling you this the distance
have to be preserved right I can swap you
and we also just remember that okay, so now
let us look at the proof of the banach explain
it so why is it called the Banach fixed point
theorem.
Because it applies in banach space right so
for different kinds of spaces that you are
starting off with you have different kinds
of fixed point there is a whole family of
fixed point theorems okay depending on the
underlying assumptions you made so this is
a fixed point theorem that we will show in
the banach space it is one of the simplest
of the fixed point theorems okay, so if you
have lesser restrictions on the underlying
space then the showing fixed points becomes
more tricky okay.
So here is the trick that will be using repeatedly
I am just taking some iterates in that sequence
right I have taken some v n and some v n plus
m plus so v n plus m occurs after v pi So
I am going to use the triangle inequality
right so I can pick some arbitrary point let
us say in between in the sequence right so
we say v n plus n+2 I can pick some arbitrary
point in the sequence which is V N + n by2
and then i can say this is less than v n +
n - v n+ n by 2 + v n + n by 2 - v nI can
write it like this some time.
Being forget about the fight they are coming
from a sequence I just think of them as three
points in space let us say v nand this some
point in that space v n plus mis some other
point in that space and this case is a third
point in that space right so once I give you
three points I can use a triangle inequality
right I just chosen the third point to be
somewhere in between in that sequence okay
so that is all I mean nothing to do with the
fact that these three points or the sequence.
I can use a triangle inequality given any
three points because I can do it this way
right but there is nothing sent no sanctity
about doing this in fact I can split this
further I can say VN + N by 2 and then N by
4 I can split that and do that in fact I can
do this for every step along the way so I
am going to replace it with this right, so
basically N+1, N+2, N+3 so it keeps doing
this repeatedly applied the triangle inequality
to get this right.
So these pick from do to
you do to you takes you and then maps another
point in you so two different points right
so I take two arbitrary points u and v this
for all points u and ? let us any arbitrary
point I take I apply T on u and I apply T
on v right so I will get two resulting points
right so I will take the distance between
them they should be less than the original
distance between u and v.
So T is a mapping from U to U it is not U
X U right it is mapping from U to U okay,
so now we have reduced it to the same T applying
multiple times right so I can apply T use
this multiple times right so what I am going
to get using this contraction operator here
is a fact was it the second stage yeah let
the operating team because we found is decreasing
the distance between the two subsequent it
had I apply the operator T.
By definition VN+ K+ 1is T operating on VN
+ K times, if it makes sense now this quantity
is independent of K so I can take it out and
sum over K so what is this sum I mean very
hard keep getting calls for a I do not know
why like my third call during the class, what
can you say about the sequence
as n and n becomes large it becomes smaller
and smaller and smaller write as n and then
becomes larger and larger.
That sequence is going to become smaller and
smaller so this is a constant so it does not
matter so N and then become larger and larger
this is going to become smaller and smaller
so what can you say the sequence V and this
cauchy okay, we will get that anything else
we can say we assume that is a banach space
right that is what I said Banach space fixed
point theorems are easy we assume it is a
black space therefore VN is convergent we
already know that right so what needs to be
shown now.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved